Guide to the Papers of Cecilia Razovsky (1886-1968), undated, 1913-1971
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, N.Y.
- Series VIII: United Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society Service, undated, 1955, 1957-1958, 1964-1965; Box 7, Folders 1-19, and Oversized Folder.
  - Subseries 2: South America, undated, 1939, 1955, 1957-1959; Box 7, Folders 8-19.
    - UHS Representative - Mexico, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Letter from Israel Jacobson to Jim Rice., August 24, 1959; September 25 and 30, 1959; October 6, 1959; 2 copies. (Box 7, Folder 15)
        He reports on the Representative's illness. Attached is a letter from Jacobson to the Davidsons, September 25, 1959. He thanks them for the profile on Mexico, and will forward the report to New York. He writes, "Glad you found Mexico peaceful and unique. I am sorry that despite the fact that the Jews are prospering they appear to be self-centered and interested primarily in their own affairs..." He notes that Razovsky will be speaking for the United Nations during World Refugee Year. Attached is a copy of a letter from the Davidsons to Jacobson, October 6, 1959. The letter responds to Jacobson's remarks concerning the Representative. Attached is a letter from Harry M. Friedman, Comptroller, United HIAS Service, New York to Razovsky, September 30, 1959. He encloses a check for expenses and compensation. Attached is a copy of a letter from Razovsky to Friedman, October 6, 1959. She is delighted with the surprise compensation. (See Item #1, #2, #6, #9)
      - Letter from Chaim Lazdeiski, Comite Central Israelita de Mexico to the Davidsons., August 31, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Letter from Chaim Lazdeiski, to Jacobson., August 31, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Jacobson., September 12, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 15)
        She writes concerning the letters from Lazdeiski (See Item #11 and Item #12).
      - Copy of contact sheet, by the Davidsons., September 1959 (Box 7, Folder 15)
        Lists the Jewish and non-Jewish persons they interviewed in Mexico City.
      - Note, by Razovsky., undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
        Her notes from her interview with Sidney Kluger, Executive Director, Centro Deportive Israelito (Jewish Sports Club).
      - Copy of report, by the Davidsons. "Mexico.", September 1959; 20 pages. (Box 7, Folder 15)
        Includes sections on Geography and Climate, the People of Mexico, History, Industry and Commerce, Education Program of the 1917 Revolution, the Labor Charter of the 1917 Constitution, Social Security, Politics and Government, Immigration to Mexico, Jewish Population of Mexico, Jewish Immigration, Socio-Economics, Jewish Community Organization, Jewish Education, Centro Deportivo Israelito, Local Jewish Philanthropy, Women's Organizations, and Mexico-Israel Cultural Relations.
      - Copy of expense report, by Razovsky., September 19, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 15)
        (See Item #10.)
    - Profile on Panama, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      - Copy of report, by Beno Klein. "Panama (Profile).", March 1958; 8 pages. (Box 7, Folder 16)
        Includes sections on the Economy, Population, Jewish Population, Jewish Community Life, Institutions and Organizations, Immigration (Possibilities and Regulations), and Contributions and Fund-Raising in Panama. Includes a list of contacts in Panama City.
    - UHS Representatives - Paraguay, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      - Copy of telegram, from Razovsky to Jacobson., March 10 and 12, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 17)
        They will not be going to Bolivia but are proceeding to Paraguay. Attached is a telegram from Jacobson to Razovsky. He writes, "Your misquoting CIME Chief embarrassing glad CIME Chile actively furthering Refugee Program..." He asks for profile material on Bolivia and Paraguay. (See Box 7, Folder 11, Item #8, Item #10, Item #11, and #13.)
      - Memorandum, from Razovsky, in San Bernardino, Paraguay to Jacobson., March 15, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 17)
        She writes of her initial impressions of the Jewish community in Paraguay and a meeting she had with their first contact in Asuncion.
      - Memorandum, from Razovsky to Jacobson., March 16, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 17)
        She met with Mr. Flatau, who is working on Polish Jewish refugees and has arranged a meeting, which she describes, with the Polish Verband Board of Directors.
      - Copy of memorandum and copy of report., March 19, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 17)
        Memorandum from Razovsky to Jacobson. She writes of her contacts the Magbit and other local Jewish organizations. She concludes her memorandum, "What is needed here is a Rabbi with missionary zeal who could build up Jewish consciousness, Jewish culture (especially amongst the children) and interest the people in a more spiritual way of life." Attached is a copy of the profile "Paraguay." Sections I: Geography and Climate; Section II: Population History and Culture; Section III: Economics (and Culture); Section IV: Immigration and Immigration Law; and Section V: The Jewish Community. A list of "Jewish Leaders in Asuncion, Paraguay" follows. Attached is a "Technical Assistance Newsletter," issued by the United Nations Department of Public Information, no. 42, May 1958. The newsletter focuses on Paraguay.
    - UHS Representatives - Peru, undated, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - Copy of telegram, from Israel Jacobson to Kaiser, HICEM, Lima, Peru., December 30, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        Jacobson informs Kaiser of Razovsky's upcoming visit.
      - Copy of daily report, by the Davidsons, Lima, Peru, January 18, 1958., January-March 1958; 2 copies. (Box 7, Folder 18)
        She reports on their meetings in Lima. Attached are copies of daily reports by the Davidsons dated February 12, 1958 and February 22, 1958. Attached is a copy of letter from Razovsky to Nissim Alalu, President, Asociacion de los Sociedades de Beneficiencias Israelitas del Peru, March 2, 1958. She has been very busy since she arrived in Peru and asks if Alalu has sent a check to Jacobson.
      - Copy of expense report, by Razovsky., January 1958; 2 copies. (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - Copy of daily report, by the Davidsons., January 20, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - Copy of memorandum, from Razovsky to Jacobson., January 26, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        She writes of competition for attention from the Jewish community leaders (there are elections taking place), and the economical depression in Peru.
      - Copy of refugee case list, by Razovsky., January 26, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        A list of pending cases in Lima, Peru.
      - Copy of memorandum, from Razovsky to Deborah Levy., January 28, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        She encloses the refugee case list (See Item #6), and writes of office matters.
      - Copy of draft agreement., January 30, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        An agreement made between the Associacion de Sociedades Israelitas Del Peru and United HIAS Service. The Associacion has agreed to serve as United HIAS Service's Representative in Lima, Peru.
      - Copy of draft agreement., January 30, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        (See Item #8.)
      - Copy of instructions, by Razovsky. "Instructions regarding correspondence on cases of refugees abroad.", February 5, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - Copy of memorandum, from Razovsky to Deborah Levy., February 19, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        The Sephardic Community needs a Rabbi in Lima; Razovsky requests Levy to forward this request to the European offices.
      - Copy of telegram, from Razovsky to Jacobson., February 19, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        Ambassador from Geneva will be arriving in São Paulo, Brazil. 53 Hungarian refugees in Rio de Janeiro have petitioned the Swedish King for assistance. Can Mr. Risk meet the Ambassador's plane? There is a vacancy for a Sephardi Rabbi in Lima, Peru. (See Box 7, Folder 12, Item #17.)
      - Letter from Herbert Gedalius, Asociacion de Beneficencia Israelita, Quito Ecuador, to Razovsky., February 19, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        (See Box 7, Folder 14.)
      - Memorandum, from Jacobson to Razovsky., February 19, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        He encloses a list of questions (not in folder) to help her with her profiles. The office is compiling a manual containing a summary of immigration laws and procedures, and needs her to find this information.
      - Telegram, from Jacobson to Razovsky., February 20, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        Has she collected contributions from Bogota, Colombia and Lima, Peru? Profiles should include immigration laws.
      - Telegram, from Jacobson to Razovsky., February 21-22, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        Lima office administrative expenses should not exceed 100 dollars monthly. Has she collected the allocation check from Lima, Peru? Attached is a copy of a memorandum from Razovsky to Jacobson. She has "solemn promises" from Bogota and Lima, but no checks. She describes her visit in Colombia. (See Box 7, Folder 12.)
      - Copy of contact list, by Razovsky. "Leading Members of the Jewish Community of Lima, Peru.", February 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - Copy of telegram, Razovsky to Jacobson. "A note about Lima.", February 25, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        She cites a reason the Jewish community in Lima, Peru does not have money for an allocation check. (See Item #15 and Item #16.)
      - Copy of memorandum, from Razovsky to Jacobson., April 10, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        The memorandum concerns Mr. Alalu, President, Asociacion de los Sociedades de Beneficiencias Israelitas del Peru, the agency serving as United HIAS Service's Representative in Lima, Peru. Alalu has not engaged a Secretary since only four families have arrived since January. She hopes to stop in Quito, Ecuador and go from there to Bogota, Colombia. She writes, "we are obviously eager to accomplish something on this last lap of our odyssey, and are making every effort to do so."
      - Copy of memorandum and report., April 10, 1958; 13 pages. (Box 7, Folder 18)
        Copy of memorandum from Razovsky to Jacobson. "Since our last visit to Lima, the Jewish community has undergone a revolution. The entire Zionist Organization blew up... A new group has reorganized the Zionist Organization... Not one name was known to us..." She met with the new Board and received promises for allocation checks. (2 copies) Attached is a copy of a report, "Peru." Sections include Geography, Climate, Population, Present Government, Economy, General Immigration, Jewish Community and Jewish Immigration, Cost of Living and Wages in General, and Immigration Laws and Regulations of Peru.
      - Telegram, from Jacobson to Razovsky., April 10, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        Jim Rice, United HIAS Service, New York is leaving for Europe and requests that Razovsky leave Mexico City directly for New York. The monthly agreement for the Mexico Representative has expired. (See Box 7, Folder 15.)
      - Telegram, from Ben Israel, Quito, Ecuador to Davidsons, Lima, Peru., April 10, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        He expects the Davidsons to arrive in Quito on Friday.
      - Copy of telegram, from Razovsky to Jacobson., undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
        Her tentative itinerary is to leave Lima, Peru on the 11th; Quito, Ecuador on the 12th; Bogota, Colombia on the 13th; Mexico City, Mexico on the 17th; Austin, Texas on the 20th; and New York on the 26th. The new leaders of the Zionist Organization have recognized the previous pledge. (See Item #20.)
      - Copy of telegram, from the Davidsons to Hans Meyer, Bogota, Colombia., April 12, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        The Davidsons are arriving in Bogota on Sunday, and ask for hotel reservations to be made.
    - UHS Report on Venezuela, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - Report, by United HIAS Service. "Venezuela; Brief and Tentative Digest of General Information and Living and Working Conditions.", November 1955 (Box 7, Folder 19)
        Sections include Climate, Population, Language, Religion, Education, Standards and Cost of Living, Employment Opportunities, Wages, Rate of Exchange, Immigration conditions, Legal Status of Immigrants, Reception on Arrival, Naturalization, and Jewish Life (Education, Religious Life, Community Life, Jewish Press). Appendix I lists wages by occupation for Caracas, Venezuela, August 1955.
- Series IX: Photographs, undated, 1953; Box 7, Folder 20.
  Razovsky is pictured in three of the four photographs that comprise this series. The fourth image is an informal wedding photograph of a couple in Germany, circa 1940s. A passport photograph of Razovsky, most likely in her 50s, provides a nice portrait. The two other photographs were taken in her later years; in the first she accepts an award in Oklahoma and in the other she is in the background in a hospital Christmas scene dated 1953.
  See also: Series I: Personal, Subseries 2: Personal Documents and Correspondence
  Note: The records of the NCJW, New York Section, I-469 has a very good photo of Razovsky.
  - Photographs, undated, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Passport size head and shoulders, in her 50s?, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Three women, Razovsky in middle, holding a piece of paper., undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
      Razovsky has a miniature around her neck of a woman. "Oklahoma" written in pencil on back.
    - Razovsky (?) as a nurse, December 16, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 20)
      In a hospital ward at Christmas, patients in the background, she's near a nativity scene that is in front of a Christmas tree.
    - Wedding photo (not of her) with two men in uniform in front of a synagogue (?), undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
      "West Side Institution..." sign in English. Written on back in pen, "Germany, Bremen, Emil". 1940s?
- Separated Oversized Material in OS1 Shared Folder, 1934, 1957, 1967
  - "The Problem of the German Refugees," by Razovsky, The Reform Advocate, pages 329-330., December 7, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Voyage to Doom," by Arthur D. Morse, reprinted from While Six Million Died, pages 59-62, 67-70., 1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Conselho de Assistencia Social, listing statistics regarding assistance to refugees in São Paulo, January 1, 1957 to August 1957; 3 pages. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Handwritten notes on the financial conditions of various refugee families., 1957; 18 pages. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Typewritten table listing Brazilian refugees, age, family members, occupation, and additional observations.